Guide to the NYU Abu Dhabi Capstone Archives AD.MC.004
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
- Social Sciences Division Projects, 2014-2019
  - Political Science
    - Maksimov, Vladislav. Silent Liberalization: The Spread and Effect of Local Popular Initiative in Texas, 2017; 2017-0045; How do policies – even those with deleterious consequences – spread across space? I address this question using a novel dataset examining locally-determined alcohol policies
      How do policies – even those with deleterious consequences – spread across space? I address this question using a novel dataset examining locally-determined alcohol policies in Texas jurisdictions from 2002 to 2014. With referenda occupying an increasingly important role on a global scale, it is essential that we understand how policies adopted through direct-democratic fora diffuse across political boundaries. I examine how policies spread via local referenda. I consider whether the choice to commence a referendum with the goal to liberalize alcohol-sales is related to similar choices made previously by residents of neighbouring jurisdictions. I find that a neighbouring jurisdiction conducting an alcohol-liberalization referendum is positively related to the likelihood of a similar referendum being conducted in the subsequent election cycle. Similarly, an increase in the number of neighbouring jurisdictions with "wet" sales policies is associated with an increased likelihood of a referendum. Finally, I do not find support for the conclusions of previous literature positing that there are costs in terms of road safety of adopting "wet" alcohol sales policies: alcohol-liberalization is not associated with an increase in drunk-driving fatalities.
    - Nichifor, Nicoleta. Blood Diamonds? Natural Resources and the Logic of Intrastate Violence in the Central African Republic, 2017; 2017-0044; The existence of extractable natural resources in countries with weak central governments is often associated with armed conflict. Yet why do some resource-rich regions in fragile states remain relatively peaceful while others are plagued with violence? This study provides a more fine-grained analysis of the relationship between natural resources and local conflict. It focuses on the case of the Central African Republic (CAR). The CAR has two regions with extensive mining areas for diamonds, the Southwest and the East. While the Southwest is the most peaceful region in the entire country, the East is severely affected by violent conflict. The project examines three commonly-cited factors that can account for the differences between the two regions: 1) type of the dominant, local armed group, 2) local governance, and 3) physical infrastructure. By using quantitative and qualitative methods, this paper shows that the primary explanation is that the East remains less connected to the central government than the Southwest, both administratively, via local governance and physically, via infrastructure. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2017-0044)
      The existence of extractable natural resources in countries with weak central governments is often associated with armed conflict. Yet why do some resource-rich regions in fragile states remain relatively peaceful while others are plagued with violence? This study provides a more fine-grained analysis of the relationship between natural resources and local conflict. It focuses on the case of the Central African Republic (CAR). The CAR has two regions with extensive mining areas for diamonds, the Southwest and the East. While the Southwest is the most peaceful region in the entire country, the East is severely affected by violent conflict. The project examines three commonly-cited factors that can account for the differences between the two regions: 1) type of the dominant, local armed group, 2) local governance, and 3) physical infrastructure. By using quantitative and qualitative methods, this paper shows that the primary explanation is that the East remains less connected to the central government than the Southwest, both administratively, via local governance and physically, via infrastructure.
    - Tyburski, Luke. Governance and Mining Sector Investment in Sierra Leone: Chiefdom-Level Analysis, 2017; 2017-0043; This paper explores the relationship between local political competition and foreign mining investment in Sierra Leone. I analyze whether subnational units (chiefdoms) with higher levels of political competition, a reasonable indicator of good governance, attract more mining investment. I further determine whether governance-based investing preferences are universal or distinct across source countries of investment. I contribute to the growing literature on the role of Chinese investment in Africa, situating Chinese investment within a larger pool of investor countries based on indicators of democracy, corruption, ease of doing business, and human development to get at causality. I use an instrumental variable, the number of ruling families per chiefdom in the colonial era, as a proxy for political competition. I find divergent patterns of investor preferences. China and South Africa fall below the median across global governance indicators, and I find that the proportion of investment from countries below the median in governance declines as the level of political competition rises. I argue that this conforms to the "familiarity" argument of investment, speculating that firms disproportionately invest in chiefdoms with similar business climates to their home countries. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2017-0043)
      This paper explores the relationship between local political competition and foreign mining investment in Sierra Leone. I analyze whether subnational units (chiefdoms) with higher levels of political competition, a reasonable indicator of good governance, attract more mining investment. I further determine whether governance-based investing preferences are universal or distinct across source countries of investment. I contribute to the growing literature on the role of Chinese investment in Africa, situating Chinese investment within a larger pool of investor countries based on indicators of democracy, corruption, ease of doing business, and human development to get at causality. I use an instrumental variable, the number of ruling families per chiefdom in the colonial era, as a proxy for political competition. I find divergent patterns of investor preferences. China and South Africa fall below the median across global governance indicators, and I find that the proportion of investment from countries below the median in governance declines as the level of political competition rises. I argue that this conforms to the "familiarity" argument of investment, speculating that firms disproportionately invest in chiefdoms with similar business climates to their home countries.
    - Alkhaili, Sultan Eisa. Income Tax Implementation in the UAE, 2018; 2018-0128 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0128)
      On January 1st 2018, the United Arab Emirates broke their tax-free reputation by introducing the VAT tax. Due to this event, there is anticipation that the next step the UAE could take may be the implementation of income tax. However, there is little research concerning the people in UAE, both citizens and residents, will react to this idea. As a result, it proved vital to perform research regarding the likely perception of these people on the intended introduction of income tax in the UAE. The study focused on the effects of the concepts of economic rationality and national duty on the citizens and residents' perception of the income tax implementation.
    - Al Ameri, Reem. Gender Parity and Happiness in the UAE, 2018; 2018-0123 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0123)
      This capstone investigates a relatively under-explored factor in the study of the determinants of a country's happiness: the effect of increasing gender equality. Using cross-national data, I first provide evidence that countries with greater gender parity have higher scores of happiness and life satisfaction, even after controlling for income and health. I then focus on the case of the UAE, where the government has actively promoted gender equality and economic opportunities for women. I use a survey experiment of approximately 400 Emirati nationals to explore how the promotion of gender parity affects each gender. Specifically, I try to understand whether increased happiness of women due to the promotion gender rights is countered by declining satisfaction of Emirati males. My survey includes several treatments of hypothetical situations to answer this question. I find that promoting female happiness raises overall happiness, as male happiness does not decline equivalently. Due to the prevalence of strong conservative gender norms in the UAE, I investigate some implications of the government's promotion of gender equality. My findings demonstrate that because Emirati women have equal opportunities in the UAE's development, this empowers them and allows them to reach their full potential, thus allowing them to be happier.
    - Asifa, Charlotte. The determinants of domestic and sexual violence: Evidence from the Congo, 2018; 2018-0145 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0145)
      What are the determinants of sexual and domestic violence in the Democratic Republic of Congo? This work aims to obtain the population that experienced domestic and sexual violence in the DRC and predict the determinants for such violence. I use the initial 2011 base survey data collected for the community driven reconstruction program, Tuungane. Using the list experiment that uniquely controls for the sensitive nature of domestic and sexual violence, I attained the portion of the population that experiences sexual and domestic violence. I use the t-test statistical method to estimate the determinants. The results showed that approximately 33.3% of the population experience sexual violence and 24.8% of the population experience domestic violence. The strongest positive determinant of sexual violence was female productivity and conflict associated with pillaging and the presence of armed groups. The strongest positive determinant for domestic violence was conflict associated with the presence of armed groups. Female productivity was a weak determinant for domestic violence.
    - Bolgari, Irina. Bandwagon Voting: Differences Between Policy Referenda and Candidate Elections, 2018; 2018-0110 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0110)
      This paper examines the manifestation of bandwagon voting behavior comparatively in two experimental treatments: candidate elections and policy referenda. The comparative study attempts to examine the extent to which giving voters information about the majority distribution impacts their preferences differently in the two contexts. This goal is accomplished by applying empirical findings on what motivates bandwagon voting, other-regarding preferences and psychological factors to the experimental analysis of the two treatments. The comparative study of the treatments shows that voters engage in bandwagon voting more frequently during the candidate elections treatment. The fact that both psychological factors and other-regarding preferences affect voters in the context of candidate elections explains the higher levels of bandwagon voting manifestation in the treatment.
    - Braunsteiner, Aron. 'Toking' Initiative: The Role of Ballot Initiatives in the Policy Diffusion of Medical Marijuana Laws, 2018; 2018-0106 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0106)
      Medical Marijuana Laws (MMLs) have been spreading in the United States for over 20 years. There are currently 29 states that have adopted a MML. What were the factors that led to the spread of this policy? When California legalised Medical Marijuana it was through Proposition 215 in 1996, a ballot initiative. This paper investigates the role ballot initiatives have played in the further adoption and diffusion of MMLs using event history analysis of MML adoptions between 1996 and 2012. I find that the presence of ballot initiatives increases the likelihood of adoption for moderate states with medium scores of liberal citizen ideology by as much as 10. I propose the mechanism that policy entrepreneurs bypass their legislatures, which are reluctant to pass MMLs unless they are very liberal, through ballot initiatives. I also find that the role of ballot initiatives has been decreasing over time, adding to the theory about their importance in the initial innovation process. I propose that as the positive policy outcomes of MMLs become more apparent establishment pressure against them fades and more states start adopting them, the role of entrepreneurship, and therefore ballot initiatives decrease and give way to other modes of diffusion.
    - Headley, Tyler. The Politics of Health, 2018; 2018-0161 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0161)
      Societal inequalities create a health gradient wherein the richer and more powerful have better health outcomes, such as higher life expectancies and lower child mortality rates, than the poorer and less powerful. While health outcomes have typically been studied within the field of public health, political Science has much to contribute to the analysis of this relationship, especially through sharing methods and theories of power and inequality. This Capstone proceeds as follows: first, I introduce the subject of public health and inequality, and describe how political Science can contribute to this subject. Second, I present three co-authored articles that serve as the core of my Capstone. The first article is a novel exploratory study on the economic costs associated with dengue illness episodes in international travelers. The second article analyzes a prospective cross-sectional cost-of-illness study at Lady Ridgeway Hospital for Children, Colombo. The third article is a bottom-up micro-costing study of the hospital-level costs associated with dengue cases.
    - Hykpo, Marie-Claude. Voting At The Extremes: A Study of Far-Right Support in France. Evidence from the 2017 Presidential Elections, 2018; 2018-0166 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0166)
      What are the determinants of support for the Front National in France? Through an analysis of electoral support for the Front National based on the results of the latest French presidential elections (May 2017), this paper aims to determine which factors influence the likelihood of supporting the Front National at the commune level. We test three different hypotheses regarding key variables which have been singled out by the existing literature as main drivers of the Front National vote; namely the presence of immigrants (Immigration), the Unemployment rate (Unemployment), the completion of a higher education degree (Higher Education) and the level of inequality (Inequality). We find that high levels of Higher Education, as well as low Unemployment, are associated with lower levels of support for the Front National; while high levels of Inequality and low levels of income both correlate with an increased Level of Support for the Front National. This paper also uncovers unexpected and negatively correlated relationships between the Level of Support for the Front National and both Age and Immigration. Moreover, the introduction of Change in Immigration overtime as a variable also reveals interesting correlations with the Level of Support for the Front National.
    - Igono, Victor. Regime type and National Health Policies: A Study of National Healthcare Expenditures in Sub-Saharan African Countries, 2018; 2018-0140 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0140)
      Does regime type influence health policies in sub-Saharan African countries? Are democratic governments likely to spend more on the health and wellbeing of their population vis-à-vis non-democracies? This paper seeks to answer the above questions by studying healthcare expenditure patterns among governments of sub-Saharan African countries. It combines a quantitative analysis of expenditure patterns among 44 African countries with an in-depth case study on two countries. The paper finds support for the positive effect of democratic polity on increased healthcare expenditure. Thus it argues that democracies dedicate a greater amount of resources to the healthcare of their populace vis-à-vis non-democracies. This is because democratic leaders have a greater incentive to provide public goods to a large section of the population in order to gain or maintain political power in the face of frequent challenge in a free and fair electoral system.
    - Jo, Hyun Woo. Political Regionalism in South Korea: An Empirical Analysis, 2018; 2018-0137 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0137)
      Previous studies on political regionalism in South Korea have pointed to the economic disparity between Yeongnam and Honam regions as a core reason. I use municipality level data on past presidential election results and GRDP per capita to further explore the relationship between the two. Analysis of GRDP per capita at the provincial level shows that the economic gap between Yeongnam and Honam has been closing over the past 30 years. However, using multiple regression analysis, I find that political regionalism is still persistent. Effects of neither GRDP per capita nor average age in Yeongnam and Honam are sufficient to offset the strong effects of region in the four most recent elections.
    - Khan, Tauqir. The Relationship Between Human Wellbeing and Firearm Related Violence in the United States of America, 2018; 2018-0162 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0162)
      This paper explores the relationship between human well-being and gun violence in the United States of America. I analyze if states with higher scores on the Human Development Index (HDI), an indicator that looks beyond a measure of simple GDP, are associated with lower rates of firearm related deaths. This is primarily to add scope to the bulk of cross-national literature that traditionally limits focus to factors such as gun ownership and mental health, and contribute to the literature connecting Health, Education and Income to crime and suicide. I find that when state-fixed and year-fixed effects are controlled, the relationship between HDI and Firearm Related Deaths becomes insignificant. Despite this, the Education Index of HDI maintains a negative relationship with Firearm Related Deaths when tested individually. As such, my findings suggest that focusing government policy on improving Education Index of a state may have positive implications on gun violence. My results also show that when controlling for HDI and Law Enforcement Officer rates, the Strength of Firearm Legislation has the strongest negative relationship with Firearm Related Deaths.
    - Klinar, Stjepan. The Sectoral Effects of Brexit on the US Economy: Early Evidence from the Stock Market Reaction to the Brexit Vote, 2018; 2018-0163 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0163)
      This paper explores the impact of the Brexit vote on publicly traded firms grouped by sectors. Based on a close examination of the immediate winners and losers from Brexit in the US, this study aims to show market expectations of future firm performance in light of the realized outcome of the Brexit negotiations. Using the market model event study methodology, I assess the effects of Brexit on stock market prices in the US stock market, relative to what had been anticipated as measured by abnormal returns (ARs). The results found no significant effect on the stock market as a whole. However, I observe significant heterogeneity of impact across sectors. Five sectors appear to be affected in particular. Utilities and Healthcare sectors experienced positive abnormal returns, while the Automobile, Business Equipment, and Banking sectors experienced negative abnormal returns. The positive abnormal returns observed in the Utilities and Healthcare sectors persist after 7 trading days; on the contrary, negative abnormal returns persist only in the Business Equipment sector. These findings indicate that Brexit had a mixed effect on the US stock market with apparent sector-by-sector differences.
    - Lino, Rafael. The Effects of Environmental Grievances on Legislative Elections in Brazil, 2018; 2018-0152 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0152)
      This paper explores the relationship between deforestation in municipalities of the Brazilian Legal Amazon, and voting preferences. I analyse whether an increase in the percentage of the deforestation of the municipality also increases support for Green and left wing parties, believed to be more responsive to environmental concerns. I use municipality and year fixed effects as control variables. I find that contrary to my hypothesis, increased deforestation is instead positively correlated to increased vote share for right wing parties, and I provide two possible explanations: Amazon residents rank economic incentives higher than environmental grievances; or that deforestation-related industries' lobbying favours right wing parties. More research is proposed in order to explore these alternative explanations.
    - Monti, Norbert. Does regime type affect the level of climate change pledges within the Paris Agreement?, 2018; 2018-0117 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0117)
      I study climate change policy with the aim of informing the question whether regime type affects climate change policies and thus environmental policies in general. I capitalize on the unique Nationally Determined Contributions to find evidence on whether the regime type of a country affects different measures of its policies presented for the Paris Agreement of 2015. I look at four measures in the Nationally Determined Contributions, namely policy type, unconditional and conditional emission reduction targets, and aggregate adaptation targets. My results reveal that policy type is largely unaffected by regime type. There is evidence that democracies in the high income quartiles have higher unconditional and conditional emission reduction targets than autocracies and anocracies. Furthermore for aggregate adaptation policies levels of corruption turn out to be a key driver, where less corrupt countries have lower aggregate adaptation policies. I infer that policy type reflects the Common But Differentiated Responsibilities principle of international law. Democracies, facing double audience costs, commit to higher tangible and monitorable targets, such as emission reduction targets. However, since aggregate adaptation policies do not lend themselves to clear monitorable mechanisms, they are used by more corrupt countries to compensate for expected international audience costs.
    - Murphy, Kelly. The Legacy of Involuntary Resettlement on Political Behaviors: Evidence from Kenya, 2018; 2018-0155 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0155)
      Involuntary resettlement affects millions of people around the world, from those displaced by natural disaster or development projects to those fleeing economic distress or conflict. In this study, I examine a villagization program from Kenya in 1953 to understand the long-term effects of involuntary resettlement. Using a novel dataset created with archival records of Mau Mau villages, I examine how involuntary resettlement in the colonial period affects political beliefs and attitudes fifty years later. I find that polling stations near villagized settlements have higher voter turnout than polling stations distant from the settlements, suggesting that individuals affected by involuntary resettlement are more politically engaged than their counterparts.